<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second epistle, being a tender salutation to the seed of Jacob vvherein is contained an exhortation to the called and chosen people of the Lord, who have kept their first love, to abide therein to the end : also, a hand of dear love held forth to the spiritual travellers, who are travelling from Egypt's land of darkness towards the spiritual land of rest : the counsel and determination of the Lord God Almighty founded in the ears of the unfaithful, disobedient and deceitful, who hold the truth in unrighteousness, and cover themselves with a profession of the precious truth, and yet live in the nature and spirit of those who walk in the broad way, that leadeth to destruction : also, a brief rehearsal and discovery of the enemy of man's soul, his workings from the beginning of his appearance unto this day, age, and generation / Charles Marshall.</title>
            <author>Marshall, Charles, 1637-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7579</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13720486</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13720486</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52030)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 846:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second epistle, being a tender salutation to the seed of Jacob vvherein is contained an exhortation to the called and chosen people of the Lord, who have kept their first love, to abide therein to the end : also, a hand of dear love held forth to the spiritual travellers, who are travelling from Egypt's land of darkness towards the spiritual land of rest : the counsel and determination of the Lord God Almighty founded in the ears of the unfaithful, disobedient and deceitful, who hold the truth in unrighteousness, and cover themselves with a profession of the precious truth, and yet live in the nature and spirit of those who walk in the broad way, that leadeth to destruction : also, a brief rehearsal and discovery of the enemy of man's soul, his workings from the beginning of his appearance unto this day, age, and generation / Charles Marshall.</title>
                  <author>Marshall, Charles, 1637-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Second EPISTLE, Being a Tender Salutation To the Seed of Jacob. VVherein is contained an Exhortation to the Called and Choſen People of the Lord, who have kept their Firſt Love, to abide therein to the End. Alſo, A Hand of Dear Love held forth to the Spiritual Travellers, who are travelling from <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Land of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, towards the Spiritual Land of Reſt. The Counſel and Determination of the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty founded in the Ears of the Unfaithful, Diſobedient and Deceitful, who hold the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs, and cover themſelves with a Profeſſion of the Precious Truth, and yet live in the Nature and Spirit of thoſe who walk in the Broad Way, that leadeth to Deſtruction. Alſo, A brief Rehearſal and Diſcovery of the Enemy of Man's Soul, his Workings from the beginning of his Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance unto this Day, Age and Generation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles Marſhall.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Ye have ſeen what I did unto the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and how I bare you on Eagles Wings, and brought you unto my ſelf. Now therefore if you will obey my Voice indeed, and keep my Covenant, then ye ſhall be a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Treaſure unto me above all People; for all the Earth is mine.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101561:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Second EPISTLE, Being a Tender Salutation To the Seed of Jacob.</head>
            <p>THou Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that haſt been ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Nations, who haſt indeed been ſmall, and lain amongſt the Pots, thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hath been covered, thou haſt been as trodden down amongſt all Nations, deſolate, and forſaken as a Widdow, thy Habitation hath been in the Wilderneſs, the great red Dragon hath ſought to devour thee, the Beaſt that roſe out of the Sea, and the Beaſt that roſe out of the Earth, and <hi>Myſtery Babylon</hi> the great have all ſought the Vailing of thy Glory, and the Deſtruction of thy Life: thou haſt been as a ſpeckled Bird, and being deſolate haſt mourned, and cried through many Ages and Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; thou haſt been as in a ſtrange Land, how hath the
<hi>Egyptian</hi> and <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> oppreſſed thee! how have the Task-maſters oppreſſed thee! Oh, thy Burdens, thy Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101561:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>thy Wounds, thy Cries and Tears, thy Lamentations, thy Groanings under all thy Oppreſſions, and Oppreſſors! thy Burden is felt, and thy deplorable Eſtate amongſt the Nations (over which Darkneſs hath ſpread it ſelf as a Covering) God Almighty hath given a ſence of.</p>
            <p>Oh thou that art as in the Clifts of the Rocks, and as in the ſecret Places of the Stairs, my Soul hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten bowed down in a ſence and ſight hereof; but (bleſſed be the Name of my God) the Sorrow hath not been without Hope, having felt the Arm that will deliver thee.</p>
            <p>Ariſe, Ariſe thou Worm <hi>Jacob,</hi> the Lord hath heard thy Mournings, and hath taken notice of thy Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and his Bowels earn on thee; yea, he hath ſeen, he hath ſeen thy deſolate Eſtate, thy Cries are come before him, and thy Sighings and Mournings; and he hath taken notice of thy Oppreſſors, and is angry with the Nations becauſe of thee.</p>
            <p>And now in the Name of the God of the whole Earth, the Everlaſting Creator, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> propheſie of thy univerſal Viſitation and Deliverance through all Nations, Tongues, and People; now will the Lord plead with all Nations for thy ſake, and give Nations for thee, and People for the Ranſom of thy Life:
<hi>Now will be gather thee, thou Seed of</hi> Jacob, <hi>from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt; he will now ſay to the North give up, and to the South keep not back, and will bring his Sons from far, and his Daughters from the Ends of the Earth;</hi> therefore thus ſaith the Lord, who redeemed <hi>Abraham,</hi> concerning the Houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob <hi>ſhall not now be aſhamed, neither ſhall his Face now wax pale; but when he ſeeth his Children, the Work of my Hands in the midſt of him, they ſhall ſanctifie my Name, and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101561:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Holy One of</hi> Jacob,
<hi>and ſhall fear the God of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>And now behold, the Name of the Lord cometh from far, burning with his Anger, and the Burden there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will be heavy; his Lips are full of Indignation, and his Tongue is Devouring Fire, and his Breath (as an Over-flowing Stream) ſhall reach to the midſt of the Neck to ſilt the Nations with the Sive of Vanity; and there ſhall be a Bridle in the Jaws of the People, cauſing them to Err: but thou Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhalt have a Song as in the Night, when an holy Solemnity is kept, and Gladneſs of Heart, as when one goeth with a Pipe to come into the Mountain of the Lord, to the Mighty One of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and the Lord ſhall cauſe his Glorious Voice to be heard, and ſhall ſhew the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning down of his Arm, and the Indignation of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and with the Flame of devouring Fire, with ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Tempeſts and Hail-Stones.</p>
            <p>And therefore Ariſe, thou Precious Seed, ſpring at the Salutation of the Prophecy of thy Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; for thou ſhalt be made a quiet Habitation, a Tabernacle that ſhall not be taken down, not one of the Stakes thereof ſhall ever be moved, neither ſhall any of thy Cords be broken; thou ſhalt be as a Royal <hi>Diadem</hi> in the Hand of thy God, even an Eternal Excellency, the Joy of many Generations, this is thy Portion, and the Lot of thy Inheritance, thou Oppreſſed Afflicted Seed of
<hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now unto you, the Firſt-Fruits of the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Day of Viſitation, which hath dawned in this Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Iſland of the
<hi>Gentiles,</hi> who have kept your firſt Love, in and through which the Lord God Everlaſting<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101561:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>reached unto you, and have kept your Habitations in the Light, unto which you were turned by the Might of the Arm of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s God, and therein have waited, and diligently ſought and ſerved the Lord; I ſay, your Bones are full of Fatneſs, your Souls are full of Vertue, and Hearts filled with the Love of God, and Minds poſſeſſed with the Pure Fear and Aw of God the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; your Tents are Goodly, and your Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Lovely; you it is I dearly love, honour and eſteem; you are the Jewels of the Lord, which he will now make up, and ſpare. My Soul is refreſhed in the very remembrance of you, and my Spirit is comforted in the ſight of you in the Inviſible Spirit of Holineſs, you Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Lord, you Amiable Ones, whoſe Souls abhor every Graven Image, and Likeneſs, nothing ſatisfying your Thirſty, Breathing, Panting Souls, but that River the Streams whereof make glad the City of God.</p>
            <p>Unto you this Exhortation ſprings in my Heart (who am a Fellow-Citizen with you) in the pure Movings and Ariſings of the Eternal Power of the Mighty One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from day to day, from week to week, from moneth to moneth, from year to year, to the very end of our dayes, let us keep our Habitations, and ſtand upon our Watch-Tower, wherein we hear what the Lord ſaith, who ſpeaketh Peace to his People, that they turn not again unto Folly; let us keep the Commandments of the Lord, cleaving to him, loving and ſerving him all our dayes, with all our Hearts, and with all our Souls.</p>
            <p>And as here all keep, we ſhall bloſſom as a Roſe, we ſhall grow as the Willows by the Water-Courſes, we ſhall mount up as on the Wings of Eagles; we ſhall run, and not be weary; and go, and not be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101561:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>faint; here every one will daily feel the Ariſings of the living eternal Power of the Higheſt, which firſt reached to quicken us, which alone can keep alive to the Lord; here Vertue is added unto Vertue, and none are barren or unfruitful, but are as a Watered Garden, being daily watered by our Beloved, who is as a Fountain of Gardens, and Well-ſprings of Living Waters, who will lead you all, you beautiful Ones, into his Banquetting-Houſe, where his Banner, even Love it ſelf, will be diſplay'd over you; wherein Eat, oh Friends, and drink, oh Friends, at the Table of the Lord, of the Fatneſs of the Houſe of our God.</p>
            <p>And oh you beautiful Flock of the good Shepherd of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> who have come up from the Waſhing, among whom there is none Barren; I am in Love with your Life, and taken with your Beauty, and the Splendour of your Garments, the fine Clean Linnen: You Virgins, your Day of Rejoycing is come, and coming; you are thoſe who ſtand with the Lamb on Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> yea, on the Sea of Glaſs, which is mingled with the Purifying Fire; you have gotten and are getting Victory over the Beaſt, and Image, and the Number of his Name; Harps are put into your Hands, and the Song of the Redeemed into your Mouthes, which none learn but the Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Lord, which is the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Servant of the Lord, and the Song of the Lamb; you have paſſed through the Miniſtration of Condemnation, which was Glorious in its Time, and are come to that which exceeds in Glory; you have ſeen, and ſhall ſee the Judgments and Deſolation of the great Whore, My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery <hi>Babylon</hi> the Great, ſhe is falling, ſhe is falling; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over her ye holy Prophets and People of the Lord;<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101561:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>an utter End and utter Deſolation in the Name of the Eternal God is coming on her, and her Merchants, and all that ſhall be found Drinking of her Cup of Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and over all that have come in, and been intre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced through the loſs of the Ancient, Pure, Holy, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Power.</p>
            <p>And ſo dear Friends, Brethren and Siſters (unto whom is the Salutation of my Love in the ariſing of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that moves me at this time thus to write) let us dwell, and forever abide, and keep, as aforeſaid, in the holy Habitation, where our Growth, Saſety and Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is forever; and the God of all Conſolation, Might, Power and Eternal Strength Water, Refreſh, and Bleſs you from this time forth, and forever.</p>
            <p>And now unto you who have been viſited with the right Arm of God's Deliverance, when you were in <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Land ſpiritual, and have been by that Arm brought forth, and are now travelling in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wherein you meet with many Tryals, and find the Snares and Temptations of the Enemy ſtrong and many, and are ready therewith ſometimes to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed, and to faint in your Minds; unto you my Heart and Soul yearns, and for you do my Bowels turn; dear Lambs and Babes, hear the Counſel of the Lord unto you in his endleſs Love, his Care is over you, that are and will be Obedient unto him, He will carry you his Lambs in his Boſom, and gently lead all that are with Young; look not at your own Weakneſs, not at the Temptations of the Enemy; neither at the Nature yet remaining, which receives the Temptations; but look to the Lord, and believe in his Power, truſt in the Sufficiency of his Grace, and let the Waves beat,<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101561:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>and the Billows of Temptation go over; ſtand you ſtill, and ye ſhall know, that he is God, who changeth not, who in his own time will lift up his Standard againſt your Enemies; who by the Arm of his own Power can make all your and his Enemies as Aſhes under the Soals of your Feet; and here you ſhall know, that the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, the Creator of the Ends of the Earth doth not ſail, neither is he weary; he gives Power to the Faint, and to them that have no Might he encreaſeth Strength: <hi>The Youths ſhall fail, and the Young Men ſhall utterly faint; but thoſe that wait upon the Lord ſhall renew their Strength; they ſhall mount up, as on Eagles wings; they ſhall run, and not be weary; and go, and not faint:</hi> Therefore lift up your Heads all you Breathing, Panting, Thirſty Ones (who cannot live without God's Appearance) in his Power your Enemies to deſtroy, the Appearance whereof your Soul loaths and abhors, even you that cannot take up a Reſt or Delight in any periſhing fading thing, but over all Mortality cries for a Saviour and Deliverer; neither can be ſatisfied with a Name to live, but cries to live to God, whoſe Souls Pant after the Loving Kindneſs of the Lord, as the Hart panteth after the Water-Brooks; whoſe Tongues ſometimes even fail for Thirſt after the Living Enjoyment of the Living God: You are belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of my Soul; your Travel I know in the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof; lift up your Heads in the Name of the Mighty God, and be no more bowed down through your long Infirmity, believe in the Anointed of the Lord, on whom your Help is laid; touch but the Hem of his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Vertue comes forth of him to heal your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed inward Man; and when the Enemy, by all his Power and Strength, would endeavour to deſtroy your<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101561:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Hope, believe in Hope againſt Hope, even againſt the Hope of the Enemy; and look not at all at your own Deadneſs, nor barren Womb, but believe in the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Seed you ſhall know that ſhall be Heir, through whom to you the Inheritance ſhall be ſure: and never ſtagger at the Promiſe, becauſe it is not preſently fulfilled; but believe (which is the Work of God) and it ſhall be imputed to you for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and in due time the Barren bears, and neither <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leazer,</hi> nor the Son of the Bond-Woman ſhall inherit, for that the Promiſes are Yea and Amen to the Seed, and to all who are in the Seed.</p>
            <p>Learn the Myſtery of Faith, which is held in a pure Conſcience, which is the Subſtance of things not ſeen, and the very Evidence of things hoped for; and here your Strength will be renewed: Caſt not away your Confidence; for that hath a Reward; nor let go your Hope, which is as an Anchor, both ſure and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt; but as I ſaid before, Believe in the Lord, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently wait upon him: never go to Battel againſt the Lord's and your Souls Enemies in your own Strength, nor Reaſon with the Enemies Appearances and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in your own Reaſon, nor conſult concerning his Appearance in your own Thoughts and Cogitations: Beware, I warn you in the Name and Love of God, of kindling Sparks of your own, which is very incident to all thus exerciſed; for the Product and Effect is to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie down in Sorrow thereof: but ſink ye down into the Death of your own Thoughts, Reaſonings and Imaginations, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings, Gatherings and Fetchings in; neither aſcend, nor deſcend, nor fly beyond the Sea; but ſink down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Word of Life in the Heart, and there in pure Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101561:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>wait patiently upon God, until he ariſe your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to ſcatter and deſtroy, and your Souls to deliver; and believe in the Word, the Light, the Gift, the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Grace, and caſt all your Care upon the Lord, who careth for you: do you nothing but ſubmit to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Grace of God; and here you will ſee and have an Underſtanding how you have in your own Strength and Wills toiled all Night, and thereby caught nothing, and in the Morning ſee your Saviour, who will direct you, ſo that by following his Directions you will ſee more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in a Moment of Time, then by your own Willing, Running and Toiling all Night; <hi>for by his own Strength ſhall no Man prevail, its God that worketh both the Will and the Deed;</hi> hear this, give ear, and be inſtructed, you affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and toſſed with Tempeſt, and not comforted; let the Scales fall off from your Eyes, then will you ſee all things poſſible, and your Faith will increaſe that removes Mountains. Ariſe you Afflicted Ones, who ſit as in the Duſt of the Earth; Ariſe, ariſe in the Might of the Power of the Eternal Strength of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſhake your ſelves from the Duſt of your own Thoughts, Conceivings, Contrivings and Imaginations; come into the Innocent Way, where the Wayfaring Man, although a Fool, ſhall not err: And be no more diſcouraged you bowed down in Soul and Spirit; li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t up your Heads in the Light of Righteouſneſs, and you ſhall ſee your Redeemer draw nigh, yea, very nigh.</p>
            <p>And ſo, dear Mourners in <hi>Zion,</hi> who mourn as a Dove without a Mate, be ye Comforted, be ye Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted; behold I declare unto you in the Word of the Lord, That if you look up unto him, and believe in his Name, and obey the Requirings of his Power, your<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101561:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Warfare will be accompliſhed, your Hearts and deſolate Souls will be inhabited with Life &amp; Love, and the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Pathes will the Lord reſtore to you; for now the Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Field ſhall become like a Wilderneſs; and you who have ſeen your ſelves like a Wilderneſs, ſhall bloſſom as a Roſe; and you who have ſeen your ſelves as a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pool, ſhall now become as Springs of Water; Night ſhall paſs over with you, and the Day ſhall dawn; Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall paſsover, and Summer draw nigh; and the Day haſteneth, you Mourners in <hi>Zion,</hi> after the Enjoyment of your God, wherein the Voice of the Turtle ſhall be heard (the Voice of the Innocent One) and the Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Birds in your Land; therefore be you comforted, ye ſolitary Ones, the Arm of the Lord is awakened for your Deliverance; <hi>break forth thou Barren that didſt not bear, for more</hi> (in the Name of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s God)
<hi>ſhall be the Children of the Barren and of the Deſolate, then of the merried Wife.</hi> And ſo dear Exerciſed Ones, ſink down in the Stayedneſs and pure Content in the Light; and I charge you, ſtrive not to ſtir up, nor awake your Beloved until he pleaſe, ſo will the Work proſper in his Hands, and you ſhall the Spoil divide, that tarry at home in your Habitation; and then you will ſee your Beloved come leaping over the Mountains, and skipping over the Hills, ye will ſee him as the Apple-Tree among the Trees of the Wood, and ſit down under his Shaddow, and find his Fruit brought forth (by his Working, and your Paſſiveneſs) pleaſant to the Taſte: ſo neither will, nor run; for the Battel is not to the Strong, nor the Race to the Swift; and here you will learn the Myſtery of your Reſting from all your Labours, that he may work, and you not let; and as you are brought to be truly paſſive, as the Clay in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101561:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Hand of the Potter; let but him (even the Lord Strong and Mighty) ariſe, and in his Ariſings your Enemies will be ſcattered.</p>
            <p>So the Lord God Almighty open your Underſtandings clearly in theſe things (which are indeed of Eternal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment) and lead you and guide you to the Fountain of Living Waters, where you may be abundantly refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, conſolated and ſtrengthned to grow ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his Might.</p>
            <p>And unto you whom the Love of God hath reached, in making manifeſt the Way of Truth, in which you ſhould walk, and who have received the Truth, and made Profeſſion and Confeſſion thereof, but have not, nor do not obey from the Heart; and all you who have taſted of the good Word of God, and of the Power of the World to come, and have and do turn aſide, and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlide from the Way of the Lord, following the Luſts of your own Hearts, and Deſires of your own Eyes, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Truth, and in ſome Meaſure are in Outward Conformity unto it, who profeſs to love God, but love the World, and the things thereof, who are Double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded and Unſtable in your Wayes, who would ſerve two Maſters, and be Heirs of two Kingdoms, who from day to day come amongſt the People of the Lord (who are Children of the Light and of the Day) but ſtill ſtand in that Nature that is Corrupt; and although in the Aſſemblies of the Lord's People ſuch may be often ſmitten, and the Way in which they ſhould walk is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and their By-Ways and Crooked Ways diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet notwithſtanding the many Reproofs of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction continue in the ſame Nature and Spirit: and all Fooliſh Virgins, who have a Lamp, but have no Oyl,<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101561:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; all who have only receiv'd the Seed in the High-Way, Stony and Thorny Grounds, who therein brings forth no Fruit to Perfection, but Diſhonour the Name of him who hath ſowed the good Seed, being one thing in Name, and another in Nature; and all you who have loſt your Firſt Love, and all you who have a Name to live, but are dead, and all you who are Luke-warm Ones, neither Hot nor Cold, who account your ſelves Rich, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in Goods, but are indeed inwardly Wretched, Miſerable, Poor, Blind and Naked, hear the Counſel of the Mighty God concerning you, Ye are the People with whom the Spirit of the Lord will not alwayes ſtrive; ye are the People who are the Sloathful Servants, not improving the Talent given and communicated unto you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye are the People that turn from the Grace of God into Wantonneſs; ye are the Backſliding Generation; ye are thoſe who make an Image and a Likeneſs, and are con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent therewith without S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bſtance it ſelf; ye are the People who profefs God, his Light, Life, Grace and Holy Way of Truth in Words, but deny him in Works, and are not Poſſeſſors of him; ye are thoſe who diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Worthy Name of the Lord amongſt the <hi>Heathen,</hi> laying Stumbling-blocks in the Way of thoſe who might come into the Way of Truth; ye are Lovers of the Unrighteous Mammon, and your Minds, Hearts, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings and Capacities are therefore ſet on work to compaſs it; ye are in
<hi>Eſau</hi>'s Nature, ſelling the Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for a Meſs of Pottage; ye will run the hazard of opening the Mouthes of the <hi>Heathen</hi> to Blaſpheme the Name of the Lord for little Gain; ye are they who have ſeen a Goodlineſs in a <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Garment, and in a Wedg of Gold and Silver; ye are of them who trample<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101561:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>under Foot the Blood of the Covenant, and do Deſpite unto the Spirit of Grace.</p>
            <p>Give eare, and hearken therefore; draw nigh to God, that he may draw nigh unto you; cleanſe your hands ye Sinners, purifie your hearts ye Double-minded Ones, leſt his Fury break forth like Fire, and there be no Remedy; bow down, and kiſs the Son, leſt his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be kindled againſt you, and ye Periſh out of the Way.</p>
            <p>I am conſtrained to ſound the Controverſie of the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God in his dreadful Name, Power and Authority with all the Unfaithful afore mentioned; and if all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned herein do not ſpeedily repent, and turn to the Lord, then ſhall your plagues be wonderful, and the Lord God will appear in the Fire of his Jealouſie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume you; and as you have, and do through diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence diſhonour the Pure Name of the Lord, ſo will the Lord God diſhonour you, and your Names ſhall rot, and be as the Dung on the Face of the Earch: God's Fury, Fire, and Plagues will deſtroy you, and ye ſhall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into the ſides of the Pit to be puniſhed with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Deſtruction from the Preſence of the Lord, and from the Glory of his Power.</p>
            <p>My Heart is filled with the Indignation of the God of Heaven, and my Quiver with the Arrows of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt the Rebellious, and Uncircumciſed: Tremble, Tremble, Tremble before the Lord, and before the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ariſings of his Power: Wo, wo, wo to the Falſe-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Deceitful, who are as broken Bowes: unto all who are covered with a Profeſſion (which is not the Covering of the Spirit of the Lord) I teſtifie God's Dreadful Vengeance, and Vialls of Wrath are near to be poured forth upon you, ye ſhall drink of the Cup of<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101561:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Fury, even the Dregs thereof with the <hi>Heathen;</hi> be ye bowed down, and dreadfully ſmitten at this Rebuk of the Lord all ye Unfaithful Ones, the Lord is offended with you, and in the Day of Trial ye ſhall be conſumed ye Reprobate Silver, ye Uncircumciſed in Heart, and Eares; you Prophane
<hi>Eſaus,</hi> who ſell your Birthright for a Meſs of Pottage; tremble ye Sinners in <hi>Zion,</hi> let fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs ſurprize all Hypocrites; God Eternal is ariſen, whoſe Spirit is upon me, and Power fills my Heart at this time, moving thereby to propheſie againſt you, and to proclaim his Controverſie with your the Day of Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Winnowing haſteneth, in which you will be winnowed from the Wheat: the Day of the Lord which burneth as an Oven cometh, and he will ſit as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finer's Fire, and Purifier of Silver, in which Day you will be ſeparated from the Gold in the purifying Fire, and thereby be conſumed: Vengeance, Vengeance, Plagues, Plagues, Fury, Fury, Calamity, Calamity, Amazement, Amazement, Aſtoniſhment, Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is coming over you, the full Cup of the Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Mighty God will be given you: I am filled, I am filled with the Fury of the Lord God of Hoſts, and am conſtrained thus to pour it forth, which, as ſure as the Lord Lives that made Heaven and Earth, will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed on you, who ſhall abide in theſe ſtates aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and not ſpeedily repent, and bow under the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Hand of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Let this go through the family and through the hearts of all the unfaithful amongſt the people of the Lord through the Land, and enter ye (when you hear theſe Words, and underſtand the Wrath determined) into the Houſe of Mourning, and Chamber of Lamentation,<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101561:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>rend your Hearts, and not your Garments; ſit in Duſt before the Lord, Repent, Repent, Repent, and as any are thus bowed down, wait that the Teſtimony of the Lord may ariſe in that Power which breaketh the hard Hearts in thoſe States and Conditions aſorementioned, that all may hear and ſear before the dread<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>l God, who will now be reverenced from the riſing of the Sun to the ſetting of the ſame, and all that do not repent, and bow before the Lord, ye ſhall be winnowed, and ſeparated from the Aſſemblies of the Lord's people, and gathered to your place, and there reſerved under Chains of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto the Judgment of the great I ay: Oh in the fence of what haſteneth to come on the unſaithful Ones have I often been bowed down, and my Soul hath in remembrance the Wormwood and the Gall in my Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels through this the Land of my Nativity, through which my God commanded me to paſs ſwittly, ſaying, <hi>Run through this Nation, and viſit my Breathing, Panting, Bruiſed Birth, which I begat among my People in the Day of their firſt Tender Viſitation: Proclaim my Acceptable Year, my Day of Perfect Deliverance to my Breathing, Panting, Earning, Tender Birth, and my Day of Vengeance to come upon that which bruiſeth it, either amongſt my People or in the World:</hi> But, Oh! ſaith my Soul, that now all the unfaithful who have trampled under Foot the Blood of the Covenant, and done Deſpite unto the Spirit of Grace, and have hitherto neglected the Day of their Viſitation; Oh, that before the Eye-lids of the Morning be to them as the Shaddow of Death, they might return to ſeek the Lord while he is to be found, and to call upon him while he is yet near, before the Everlaſting Night comes, in which no man can work.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101561:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>DEar Friends, great hath been the work, and many have been the Devices of the old Crooked Serpent, (even of him who kept not his firſt Habitation) to draw the Sons and Daughters of Men from their God through Ages, and Generations; and after every Appearance of the Lord God (wherein his eminent Hand hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Arm hath been ſignally manifeſt) the Enemy hath endeavoured by divers wayes to deſtroy the Work of God, ſometimes by filling Inſtruments with Enmity to oppoſe the Appearance of Truth by Perſecution, and things of that nature; and when that could not prevail, (the Power and Arm of God Almighty getting Victory over it) then he hath transformed in Appearance like unto an Angel of Light, approving and leading into the Practice of that outwardly, which before in his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he had withſtood, but ſtill hath ſeparated from the Truth, and hath ſo deceiv'd the minds of the Sons of Men, as that their co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>formity and obedience ſhould not be really in Spirit and in Truth, but in the Name and Profeſſion only: and on this wiſe he began his appearance with the firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> thereby drawing him from the Tree of Life, and out of the Image of God, and brought him into that State in which he could no longer dwell in the Garden of the Lord, and after corrupted the Sons of men, that they grieved their God; ſo as that of all upon the Earth he found <hi>Noah</hi> Upright, and ſaved him,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101561:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and his Houſe, and deſtroyed all Mankind from off the Earth; and when Men began to multiply upon the face of the Earth, the old Enemy led them to build that which God took no Delight in, and therefore he came down and confounded them, and ſcattered them: but <hi>Abraham</hi> he called from his Fathers Houſe beyond the Flood, who obey'd the Voice of God, and believ'd in him, and did cleave to the Lord with all his Heart and Soul, and obey'd; to whom the Lord promiſed, <hi>To multiply his Seed as the Starrs of Heaven, and as the Sand on the Sea-ſhore;</hi> and covenanted with him in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and gave him <hi>Iſaac</hi> in which the Seed was called, of whom this Seed was to ſpring that was to be as the Sand of the Sea, and Stars of Heaven: then <hi>Abraham</hi> being required to offer him up, reaſoned not with the Lord, nor diſobeyed the Voice of his Maker; but took the Lad, and the Wood, and the Knife, and went to the Land of <hi>Moriah,</hi> to the Mount which the Lord had ſhewed him; but the Lord, after he had proved him, ſpared <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the <hi>Ram</hi> was offer'd up: of which
<hi>Iſaac</hi> came <hi>Jacob,</hi> in whom the Seed was multiplied; which
<hi>Jacob</hi> wreſtled with the God of his Fathers for a Bleſſing, and prevailed with God, and then was named <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of whom came the Children that went down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aegypt</hi> to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who was hated of his Brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his Dreams; afterwards <hi>Iſrael</hi> multiplied into a People, who were Oppreſſed by <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who knew not <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and would have deſtroyed the Seed of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> and have hindred them from multiplying, howbeit God preſerv'd <hi>Moſes</hi> (that goodly Child) who was drawn out of the Waters, who when he was keeping his Father-in-Law <hi>Jethro</hi>'s Sheep, and drave them to the Backſide of<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101561:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Deſart, and came to <hi>Horeb,</hi> the Mountain of God, then the Lord appeared in the Buſh in a Flame of Fire, ſaying, <hi>I have ſurely ſeen the Affliction of my People which are in</hi> Fgypt, <hi>and have heard their Cries, by reaſon of their Task-Maſters; for I know their Sorrow;</hi> and the Lord God by the Hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> wrought Wonders in the Land of
<hi>Egypt,</hi> and plagued <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and brought <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi>'s I and by an Out-ſtretched Arm, and by a Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Hand through the Red Sea, on the Banks of which they ſang the Song of Deliverance; but the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy that ſtirred up <hi>Pharoah</hi> to oppreſs them, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from coming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> moved in their Hearts to diſobey the Lord, and to-draw them from a Belief in that Power which had ſo ſignally delivered them; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Merciful God of <hi>Jacob</hi> healed the Waters, and notwithſtanding cauſed the <hi>Manna</hi> to come down Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by Morning to ſeed them, he alſo ſmote the <hi>Flinty Rock;</hi> and brought forth Waters; after they thus mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured he brought them to
<hi>Sinai,</hi> where the Glory of the Lord appeared, and there gave them a Law and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts; but notwithſtanding they had ſeen the Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Hand of the Lord, and his ſignal Deliverances, were fed and preſerved by him, yet they murmured in their Hearts againſt the Lord, and through the Workings of the ſame ſubtil Enemy (to whom they gave way) made Godds of Gold, and in their Hearts would have gone back again unto <hi>Egypt,</hi> and Rebelled againſt the Lord, and ſo the Enemy of Mankind the Devil prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that after the Spies had ſpied the Land they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured againſt the Lord, and againſt his Servants, ſo as that the Lord deſtroyed them, and their Carkaſes ſell in the Wilderneſs to whom the Promiſe was, ſave <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101561:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>Caleb,</hi> Men of another Spirit; howbeit
<hi>Joſhua</hi> led their Children over <hi>Jordan</hi> to poſſeſs the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> unto whom the Lord was good, and performed all the good Things promiſed; and they drave forth the Inhabitants of the Land, and inhabited it; and here the Enemy <hi>Satan</hi> prevailed again, ſo that
<hi>Jeſurum</hi> waxed ſat, even thick, and kicked, and then he forſook God that made him, and lightly eſteemed the Rock of his Salvation, and went and ſerved other Godds, and the Lord delivered them into their Enemies Hands; howbeit when they were brought low the Lord heard their Cries, and delivered them by the Hands of many Inſtruments, which he raiſed up as
<hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even unto the time of
<hi>David,</hi> who ſound Favour before God, and deſired to find a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle for the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> by whom he delivered
<hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> who went out in the Strength of the Mighty God, and ſought their Battels, whoſe Heart loved the Lord, whoſe Name is a Sweet Memorial: but <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son built a Houſe for the God of
<hi>Jacob,</hi> and the Temple that was a Figure, and the Lord was with him and
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> and his Glotious Preſence was amongſt them; howbeit the Old Subtil Enemy that deceived <hi>Adam,</hi> turned <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Heart from following the Lord, to follow other Godds, and built a Place for the Godds of the <hi>Heathen;</hi> after which the Enemy fill'd the Heart of
<hi>Jeroboam</hi> to do wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> departed from the Lord; howbeit the Lord ſent his Prophets ariſing early, to whom they did deſpitefully, even to <hi>John,</hi> a Prophet and Fore-runner of the
<hi>Meſſiah,</hi> whom they beheaded, and ſlew the Juſt One, the Anointed of the Lord, and believed not on him who was the Heir, notwithſtanding the Mighty<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101561:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Works which he did, who was manifeſt in due time, taking not on himſelf the Nature of Angels, but the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who ſent the Comforter, the Spirit of Truth, the Holy Ghoſt, which came upon the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and filled them, through whom the Power of the Moſt High God was ſignally manifeſt, ſmiteing Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands at the Heart; and in that Day many were added to the Church, and great Grace was upon them; and there was in that Bleſſed Day of the great Appearance of the Mighty God daily the Revealings and Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings of his Eternal Power, ſo that great Fear came on the Regions round about, and the Word of God grew; but preſently the Roaring Lion (that through Ages went about to deſtroy the Appearance of the Lord God) by his Power ſtirred in the Hearts of the Ungodly to oppoſe that Appearance, over whom the mighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Lord gave his Servants much Victory; yet he ceaſed not, but transformed as an Angel of Light, and in his Inſtruments wrought to draw People from the Power of Godlineſs, into the Form of Godlineſs, and brought in damnable Hereſies privily, through his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments that aroſe amongſt the People of the Lord, and in that day he wrought powerfully, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church was in the Glorious Splendor of the Heavenly Celeſtial Life <hi>(as a Woman cloathed with the Sun, having the Moon under her Feet, and on her Head a Crown of twelve Stars)</hi> and travelled, and brought forth the Man-Child, who was to rule the Nations with a Rod of Iron, yet he in the Appearance of a Red Dragon <hi>(who had the ſeven Heads, and ten Horns, and ſeven Crowns on his Heads)</hi> ſtood ready to devour the Man-Child; but he was caught up to God, and to his Throne; and the Woman having
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101561:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>two Wings as of a great Eagle given her, fled into the Wilderneſs for a Time, Times, and a half, from the Face of the old Serpent, and he hath made War with the Remnant of her Seed, and by his powerful Workings brought Night over again, who work'd myſteriouſly even amongſt the Churches, cauſing ſome to loſe their Firſt Love, others to hold the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> others the Doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans;</hi> others to have a Name to live, and yet dead to God; others ſuffered the Woman
<hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel;</hi> others called themſelves <hi>Jews,</hi> and were not, but were in the Nature of the Synagogue of Satan; others there were that were Luke-warm, neither Hot nor Cold: and manifold have been the Transformings of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary of Mankind the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>evil, but in one and the ſame Nature and Power. His firſt Appearance under which he would have deſtroyed the Man-Child, and the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the Remnant of her, was a great Red Dragon, then as a Beaſt riſing out of the Sea (the Waters) who had ſeaven Heads and ten Horns, and on his Heads ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Crowns, and the Beaſt had his Power, Seat and great Authority from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ragon; and <hi>John</hi> ſaw ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Appearance, a ſecond Beaſt, that roſe out of the Earth, which Beaſt had only two Horns, and that like a Lamb, but ſpake as a Dragon, and exerciſed the Power of the firſt Beaſt, which firſt Beaſt (having a Wound by the Sword and did live) all the World wondered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who had made War with the Saints and overcame them, and all worſhipped (and do worſhip) the Beaſt (that had a Wound and did live) whoſe Names are not written in the Book of Life of the Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World; if any Man hath an Ear to hear let him hear: Here is Wiſdom, let him that hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101561:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Underſtanding count the Number of the Beaſt, who carryed <hi>Myſtery Babylon the great, the Mother of Harlots,</hi> who was drunken with the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> Oh horrible Night! Oh deplorable Time and Seaſon that hath been over all the Nations, Tongues and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple this Forty and Two Moneths, all which time the holy City hath lain trodden under Foot, and this Thouſand two Hundred and Sixty Dayes, which time the Witneſſes have Propheſied in S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>k-cloth and Aſhes, and have been ſlain by the Beaſt, whoſe dead Bodies have lain ſlain three dayes and a half in the midſt of the great City (not put into Graves) which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where alſo our Lord was crucified; the Woman which was clothed with the Sun hath been in the Wilderneſs a Time, Times, and an half, the Book of Life was ſealed with ſeven Seals. But now that which lies on my Spirit is to manifeſt, that this horrible Night of Apoſtacy entered at firſt through the departing of ſome from the Power, even the Power of Godlineſs it ſelf, into the Form thereof, through which came into the Churches the before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned horrible Evils; And this Depature from the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is occaſioned through going out of the Daily Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in the Gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of God (in which and through which the Power of the Almighty is daily felt and manifeſted) and through the getting up of that Wiſdom that is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, in which the cunning Serpent the Devil wrought to bring in Damnable Hereſies privily; for this is the Treacherous Part in Man, in which the Devil hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared againſt the Life, the Truth, the Power in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Generations; for herein he makes a Likeneſs of the Truth, and thereby and therein ſetteth up Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions,<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101561:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Rules, and Limits to the Spirit and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God it ſelf, and thoſe born of it; and this is that which hath and would kill the Heir, the Life, that Self may have the Inheritance; and this birth of the Evil One leadeth to ſacrifice to their own Net; and herein the Apoſtacy came in privily, cunningly and gradually, and improved it ſelf through the Workings of the power of the old ſubtil Serpent, in his Transformings as an Angel of Light, in the Wiſdom of Men, which is from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, and is ſenſual: For that which cauſed the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Lord Jeſus in the Apoſtles dayes to be Glorious, was not the Wiſdom of Man aforemention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the Out-goings, and Daily Ariſings, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Operations of God's Eternal Power and Spirit, in which no Graven Image, Likeneſs or Similitude can be ſet up; for that's the Work of the Devil in the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Will of Man that acts (like the Devil) of it ſelf apart, and without the daily and continual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealings of the Eternal Power of God Almighty; and all Knowledge either gathered by, or ſtanding here, puffeth up, and at laſt leads to forſake the Life and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, like
<hi>Demas.</hi> But now dear Friends (ever-bleſſed be the Name of the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and all the Faithful through Ages and Generations paſt) the Lord God of Heaven and Earth hath cauſed his Ancient Power and Arm to be reveal'd after this ſore horrible Night of Darkneſs, that hath been in and over the Earth, and the good Old Way, and Ancient Path of Life is again revealed, into which Thouſands and Ten Thouſands have been called, and many have been gathered; Magnified and Praiſed be his Name for it, let it be given and returned to him through Ages and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101561:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>even for evermore, for that he hath remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and viſited again the Diſtreſſed in the Wilderneſs, and is bringing forth the Deſolate, ſo that now ſhe is ſeen <hi>leaning on her Beloved; and Life from God is entered into the two Witneſſes; and the Seven Seals are opened, and opening; and great.</hi> Babylon <hi>is come in Remembrance before him, to be ſunk down, and deſtroyed by a perpetual Deſtruction; and now</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is coming down as a Bride adorned for her Husband, the Seven Thunders uttering their Voices, the Perfection of Shaking, that the Myſtery of God may be finiſhed.</hi> But dear Friends, the ſame <hi>Roaring Lyon,</hi> that appeared in the Ages by-paſt, is now going about, and that diligently, ſeeking how he may deſtroy this Appearance of the Mighty God in this Age and Generation, by drawing the Mind and Heart gradually aſide from the Eternal Power it ſelf that firſt viſited, and alſo through his many Inſtruments (op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Truth) that are led captive at his Will: And now dear Friends, there is no
<hi>Preſervation</hi> but in keeping to the <hi>Simplicity of the Goſpel,</hi> and to the very <hi>Living Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power of the Lord God,</hi> by which all being kept low, <hi>Self</hi> (and that part aforementioned that the Enemy work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in) <hi>will be made of no Reputation;</hi> but be humbled to <hi>Death,</hi> even the very <hi>Death of the Croſs,</hi> which is the
<hi>Power of God;</hi> and here let all keep in the <hi>pure Retiredneſs,</hi> in the <hi>Valley of Humility,</hi> in pure <hi>Dread, Fear</hi> and <hi>Awe:</hi> and let that be your <hi>Inſtructor</hi> and
<hi>Teacher</hi> that hath been leaſt, and not the <hi>Wiſdom of Man;</hi> for that will lead in <hi>Nature</hi> from the <hi>Power,</hi> although in
<hi>Name</hi> own and ſpeak thereof. And dear Friends, a Travel hath been on my Spirit beyond all expreſſion, <hi>That the Enemy may never deceive any of us, as he did</hi> Eve <hi>by Subtilty;</hi> for this I declare in the Name of the Lord God, <hi>The Enemy worketh no way which hath a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101561:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>more ſecretly deſtructive to the Appearance of the Moſt High God in this day, then in the Wiſdom of Man, which is not that Wiſdom that is from above, which Wiſdom is pure and peaceable, the Nature of which is to lay low all, as the Nature of the other which is ſenſual, is to make Men and Women grow</hi> Jeſurum <hi>like, thick, and fat, and high, which leads and turns from the Broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, Tender, Contrite-ſpirited eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo dear Friends, in the Bowels of unexpreſſible Love to all that have been viſited with the <hi>right Arm of God's Salvation,</hi> and are <hi>tender before the Lord,</hi> keep in the <hi>Light,</hi> in a
<hi>daily watchful Eſtate;</hi> for if there be not a keeping here, <hi>a good State and precious Growth in the Truth may ſoon be loſt, and an Image of the thing come up in its place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God Almighty in his <hi>Heavenly Power,</hi> &amp; by the working of his <hi>everlaſting quickning Spirit,</hi> open unto you all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<hi>Snares</hi> &amp; <hi>Wiles of the Enemy,</hi> by which he lies in wait the
<hi>Innocent to deceive,</hi> and preſerve all in the Gift of his Love, in the ſight and knowledge thereof, <hi>that by the daily Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation and Operation of his pure Power we may break all the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Snares, &amp; in the ſame live to his Glory to the end of our days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all Friends every where, all to your <hi>Tents, dwell and walk with the Lord, build on the ſure Foundation, the try'd Corner-Stone,</hi> which they only do who hear the Word of the Lord, and do it; ſo ſhall you and your Building ſtand in the <hi>ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Day,</hi> that comes to try all Foundations and Buildings, <hi>in which day the Floods will come, the Waves will beat, &amp; the Rain deſcend, and then all Sandy Foundations, and all Buildings, how ſtately ſoever built thereon, ſhall fall, and great will be their Fall and perpetual Deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo the Lord God preſerve you all, to build and be eſtabliſh'd on the <hi>Foundation of many Generations,</hi> ſo will you go through the <hi>Fiery Tryal,</hi> in which nothing ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101561:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>but the <hi>Droſs, Lead, Tin</hi> and
<hi>reprobate Silver; for the Gold will endure the Tryal, and the Wheat the Fanning, but the Chaff will be blown away, and all the Stubble conſumed by the dreadful purifying Fire of God that will try all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord gather the <hi>Upright</hi> into the <hi>Ark of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and into the <hi>Munition of Rocks,</hi> where <hi>Bread</hi> will be ſure to the <hi>Hungry Ones,</hi> and <hi>Water</hi> to the
<hi>Thirſty;</hi> in which Eſtate the God of the Spirits of all Fleſh preſerve and keep his <hi>Flock</hi> and <hi>Family</hi> every where, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly <hi>water, dew upon</hi> and <hi>Repleniſh His,</hi> even from this time forth and forever and ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Marſhall.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Tetherton</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi>
                  <date>the 7th of the 1ſt Moneth, in the Year,
1673.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
